Ultimate promise of God to
the patriarchs. When you read about God's promise to
Abraham, God's promise under
the Old Covenant, The fulfillment
of all the promises of God is in
the giving of the Spirit. Glory to God!
Hallelujah! So there are many
scriptures that talked about the giving
of the Spirit. God pouring out his Spirit upon
all flesh. God puts in his Spirit in
the hearts of men and all that. And here God
told Zechariah, he said he's going to pour out
the spirit of grace and supplication.
And anywhere God talks about the giving of a spirit
or the promise of a spirit, he often indicates
a particular ministry of the Holy Spirit
or what the Holy Spirit is going to do in the life of
his people. Hallelujah! You know,
he told Ezekiel, he said that he's going to take
a stony heart out of them and then he will give
them the heart of flesh. He said they will give them the Spirit,
and what the Spirit is going to do is that the Spirit is
going to enable them to walk according
to his will. The Spirit is going to enable
them, and that is what we call the fruit of the Spirit. Hallelujah!
But here God told Zechariah, he said
he will pour his Spirit upon his people,
and then he gave a specific description of
what the Spirit is going to accomplish.
He said the Spirit of grace and supplication.
Say after me, say the Spirit of grace. Hey, louder, say the
Spirit of grace and supplication.
So it means that the ministry of the Holy Spirit is
going to cover the prayer aspect of the believer's life.
You know, we, we take so many things for granted
as believers, especially for those who are filled with the Spirit.
And you know, David looked into our day.
I know what he said. He said, blessed is the man unto whom
God will not impute sin.
He said, blessed are those whose sins are forgiven.
So it means that while you, you know, admire David's
walk with God, he's a man after God's heart, David looked into
your days. And he said that I want, I desire what
these people have. Amen.
You know, it was Jesus was talking to the Jews and he told them,
he said, see, greater than Solomon is here.
In fact, he told them, Solomon in all his glory was not
as clothed as this grass.
Hallelujah! Praise God! And what is he saying?
He's saying that you have it better now than
they had it. Say after me, say, I have it better now.
Hey, louder, say, I have it better now.
You know, when you read the story of, you know,
the prophets and the patriarchs, their encounter with God,
you are tempted to desire those kind
of encounter. Amen.
Wouldn't you like to be the one walking through
the Red Sea on dry ground? Amen.
How many of you will not mind eating manna for 40 years? I know
many of you because you like food. You don't even understand the context. Praise God.
But you see, we have it better in the New Covenant
than they had it under the Old Covenant.
Is that very clear? Okay, so, so I was talking
about the promise of God. So he said that I'm going to pour
out the spirit of grace and supplication,
and that is very profound. It means that as believers,
you will never need to struggle
with your prayer life. You know,
the problem with many Christians is that We like what
God promised in his word, but we do not pay attention
to how to come into the experience of that promise.
For example, you say people like prosperity. There's nobody that doesn't like prosperity,
but people don't walk in obedience.
Hallelujah! Praise God forevermore!
Just like you, you like to have a
fervent prayer life, you would love to be
the kind of person that every moment of your life
you are living it in prayer.
But you see, you need to understand the
way that God has made available for that possibility.
So he told them, he said, I will pour the Spirit of grace and
supplication, which means that one of the expressions or the
ministry of the Holy Spirit in the lives of my people is
the enablement to pray.
Is that very clear? Enablement to pray.
In fact, you know, Bible says that God has
given us the Spirit of sonship
whereby we cry, Abba, Father.
So it means that the cry of the believer
is enabled by the Spirit.
Many Christians are not conscious of the presence and
the ministry of the Holy Spirit in their life, and that is the sole reason
why many people are struggling. So you need to understand
that the Christian life is designed
to be empowered by the Holy Spirit.
You are going to struggle in your walk with God. You are going
to struggle in your prayer life. You will struggle with
Bible study. You will struggle with your entire
Christian life Until you are
conscious, you practice the presence
of God.
And practicing God's presence, it simply means that
you being conscious of the presence of the
Holy Spirit in your life.
Amen. I'm driving out somewhere this evening. Praise God
forevermore. Praise God forevermore.
So God said, I'm going to pour out the spirit of
grace as supplication. So that means as
a believer, you will not have to see— now pay
attention to me— anytime you find yourself struggling—
now the reason many people don't have a prayer life is that they,
they struggle to pray. But then you need to understand
the provision of God out of that position,
it is the Spirit. Is that very clear?
So God does not want you to try to reach out to him through
your sheer human efforts.
He has made a way in the Holy Ghost.
Say, God has made a way for me in
the Holy Ghost. He has given
us the Spirit, he said, whereby we cry,
Abba, Father. Now let me, let me read some scriptures to you so that you
can, you know, appreciate the
ministry of the Holy Spirit in your
life as believer.
Let's see Romans chapter 8, verse 26.
Likewise the Spirit also helps our infirmities,
for we know not what we should pray for as we ought,
but the Spirit himself maketh intercession
for us with groanings which cannot be uttered.
And he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what
is the mind of the Spirit, because he maketh
intercession for the saints according to the will of God.
Praying— okay, sorry. So it says he maketh intercession for the saints
according to what? The will of God. So we see in this text
that prayer is meant to
be aided by the Holy Spirit.
Prayer is what is meant to be aided by the Holy
Spirit. It says he helps our infirmities. Now the
infirmities here is not talking about medical condition. All right,
it is talking about the limitation of the man,
the limitation of the mind, the limitation of the human
strength, the limitation of the human understanding.
Praise God. So Bible says the Holy Spirit
helps this limitation, for we know not what
we should pray for as we ought. We don't know what we should
pray for as we ought. Amen. Oh, glory to God.
Glory to God. See, you owe it to God to fulfill
your purpose on earth.
You owe it to God to fulfill your purpose on earth because you
have the Holy Spirit. There's nobody—
no believer should have an excuse of
not having a robust prayer life
A vibrant prayer life because you have
the Holy Spirit. He says, this is one
of the reasons why I've given you the Spirit. He is the Spirit of grace
and supplication. So he helps
our infirmities, he bears us up in the
time of weakness, in a time
of trouble. He helps our inadequacy.
He taketh all together with us. Hallelujah!
He taketh all together with us.
Oh, praise God forevermore.
Ephesians chapter 6, verse 18. Now I'm just laying foundation
for what I'm going to be teaching this evening. Ephesians 6:18,
praying always with all prayer and supplication in
the Spirit, praying always with what?
All prayer and supplication in the Spirit.
All prayer. Somebody say all prayer, including the one
you pray in your bathroom, including the one you pray in the kitchen,
plus the one you pray behind the wheels when you are driving. It says all
prayer in the Spirit. So God— now
please pay attention to me— so God never anticipates
any moment of your life or any moment
of prayer prayed without the aid of the
Are you getting what I'm saying here? Okay, let me repeat myself.
God never anticipates,
God never expects you to pray any prayer,
whether a casual— what you call a casual prayer. You know, I've taught you
this, that as believers you must learn how to place premium on your prayer.
As believers, there's nothing like casual prayer. Your 1-minute
prayer can work wonders. See, the potency of your prayer
has a lot to do with the value, the weight you place on it,
the expectation, the confidence in your heart that this prayer
will produce results.
Because for many reasons, for many people, the reason they are not seeing results
in their prayer life is not even because they are not praying well. It's even
not because they are not praying without the consciousness— it is not because they are
praying without the consciousness of the Holy Spirit. It's not because they are not following
the principles that govern prayer. The problem is that they do
not have expectation. They do not place premium
on their prayer. I don't have anything called casual
prayer. I've seen cripple walk with casual prayer.
I've seen the dead risen back to life with what you call casual prayer.
Because many times, maybe, maybe the difference between you
and an anointed man of God, all right, is the value
placed on prayer.
And that is why I tell you If it occurs to you
that, hey, you've not been praying, right there at that moment,
start praying. The prayer you pray at that moment is not
less powerful, is not less effective than the
one you pray when you clear your schedule. Are you getting what I'm saying here?
You may just be able to generate more power.
But you know the interesting thing? When Bible talks about the tremendous power that
is made available The tremendousness of that power is not
primarily in volume. It is in the essence and the nature of
that power. Because see, the effectiveness of the things of the Spirit
is not measured by volume. That's why when the disciples said that,
hey, pray for us that our faith will increase—
see, this thing, the things of the Spirit, is not primarily
by volume.
It is you placing premium.
Are you getting what I'm saying? Say, I have no casual
prayer. Praise God.
Say, even my casual prayer— louder—
say, even my casual prayer causes casualties
in the camp of the enemy.
There's nothing like casual prayer.
Glory to God, praise God forevermore.
So Bible says praying all prayer,
praying always, always.
That is the frequency of your prayer.
Then he said all prayer.
All prayer. Last week I taught you different kinds
of prayer. Praise God. I taught you prayer of intercession.
I taught you supplication. I taught you prayer of inquiry,
prayer of consecration. I talked about commanding prayer.
Praise God forevermore. And the other prayer I can't even
remember now. Prayer of what? Oh,
worship. Thank you very much. So you see, all this prayer— he said
you pray all prayer in the Spirit.
So it means that God never expected you.
He knows that you have infirmity in your flesh.
He knows that you can wake up without appetite for prayer.
He anticipated it.
The more your low moment is not a shock to God. God is not offended.
God is not grieved by your low moments. He anticipated it,
and then he made provision in the Holy Ghost. He said, I will give you
the spirit of grace and supplication.
Amen. You know the reason many people don't
have effective prayer? Their prayer is not generating enough
impact. It's because they have mental picture.
Of what powerful prayer looks like.
And devil likes that mindset.
Devil will keep using the picture to guilt-trip you, and you can never rise
to do what you are— you can never rise above what you are guilty
of.
Have you struggled with a bad habit and you really feel
guilty about it, but the feeling of guilt never stops you?
From repeating it. Devil just
like you to— he likes to guilt-trip you.
So you have a mentor that they told you the way, ah, the way Ayobabalola
prayed. Amen. And then we found out that some
of those stories were not even really true. Of course some
are true, but even if all the stories are true,
it was the Spirit. I don't want to get ahead of myself because I'm still
going to get to that in this teaching. So you need to understand that I
said something, I think I did a video, I don't know whether it is out,
that you see, as a believer, you must learn to find your rhythm
in the spirit.
Is that very clear? You should what? Find your
rhythm. Now, while you are trying to discipline yourself to
wake up in the midnight to pray, don't live in condemnation
to now think the one you pray in the morning or afternoon is not effective.
Because now you see some, some folks will
talk about, you know, how we did 18 hours and
all that. And as I always say, it is good for you to have such
discipline. You should have moments where you just stretch
in the place of prayer. I'm planning we're going to do that in the
month of September. If you pick a prophecy I gave while I was preaching,
was it on Sunday? September we are stretching. September we are stretching.
Because anytime you will receive a word on stretching,
let your first response to be in prayer.
Because prayer is how we stretch the borders of our hearts.
But then you see, you must understand— now you will agree with me that
there was actually nowhere in scripture that shows that
the apostles, they prayed 24 hours at stretch. Are you getting
what I'm saying here? Now, what I am communicating to you is this: never
allow the devil to guilt-trip you.
You will never— you will never— see,
it doesn't matter your intention, you will not be able to rise up
in prayer when you keep having guilt.
That's why I said that the prayer of a righteous man— so you need the
consciousness of that righteousness for you to rise up.
What condemnation does is that it suppresses your prayer life.
Have you made up your mind to pray for them? You remember one bad thing
you did. Maybe now you have better light. Maybe when you
were growing up in faith and all that, you just remember one bad thing that
you did, and right there is as if they pour ice water on
you and all your excitement, the passion just got
That's the spirit of religion. Find your reading and
then grow with it.
Is that very clear? Amen.
All prayer Louder, say after me. Say, all prayer.
Louder, say, all prayer. I can't hear you. Say, all prayer.
All prayer and supplication. A what?
In the spirit. So one
of the ministries of the Holy Spirit in your life is to supply
all the aids that you need to pray. So God
never expects you to pray any prayer
outside the help of the Holy Spirit. The reason many
Christians are struggling with prayer is because they do not have a
conscious relationship. Now, whether you are conscious of the presence of
the Holy Spirit or not, you have a relationship with him.
But you need to have a conscious relationship with
the Holy Spirit, and that is what we call the practice of God's
presence. And one of the things the
practice of the presence of the Holy Spirit does is this: it helps you to
pray spontaneously.
Do you know they, they asked Smith Wigglesworth, they said,
sir, please tell us— how many of you know
Smith Wigglesworth? Praise God. I think we should be having criteria
to admit people for hearing of faith. How many of you know Smith Wigglesworth?
All right, now you, you hear the amazing things that God did through this man
of God. Amazing things. He raises the dead as if he's
waking people from sleep. Now they asked him, they said, please tell us your spirit,
tell us, tell us your secrets,
tell us your secrets. We know that this thing can never be
possible without a robust prayer life.
Tell us your prayer secrets. And he
said that I have never prayed more than 30 minutes.
I've never prayed more than 20 minutes at a time in my life,
but there is no 20 minutes that pass without
me praying because
there is no formula to this thing. Now, when we
encourage you to do a minimum of 1 hour in tongues daily,
it is to stretch, it is to exercise yourself,
because the thing is this: If you can do 1 hour praying in tongues on
daily basis, it's just like you exercising.
You are doing morning walk, morning jog, and all that.
Now if they tell you that, hey, bandits are here, you have the
stamina. And see, that you see danger does not mean that
you have the strength to run.
Yoruba has a saying, that a forlorn
crippled man will
not be a victim of war, because before the one will
come close, he knows his condition, he would have vanished.
Amen. Praise God forevermore. So you must
learn to find your rhythm. He said, I have never prayed for more
than 20 minutes. So if he says he has never prayed for
more than 20 minutes, that means that at a stretch he prays under
most 20 minutes. Look at the great things
that God did with him. Oh,
Pastor is saying that I can now reduce my prayer to 20 minutes. That's your
cup of tea. Praise God.
You know, I, I remember when I just started out
in ministry And then I devoured— oh my God,
I have read virtually everything that Kenneth Hagin ever
wrote, including manuscripts that didn't go
into publication.
And then I stumbled on one of his books, and when he said that he
has never fasted for more than 3 days, I was angry
that, God, are you a racist? Why is it that this thing is so easy
for these Oyinbo people but for us? See, at that moment I began
to pay more attention to Oyinbo minister. Because if you listen to an African
pastor, they just make this thing to look so lofty you cannot attain it.
It is spiritual elitism.
Even Jesus said that greater works than me— thank God that it was not an
African man. Jesus was not an African man. You want to raise the
dead, you know what, you know this thing now. You want to raise the dead,
ah, you will need to first do 12
hours, 6 months at stretch,
then you add midnight to it.
Then by then we know that you are ready. You can't hear those. How many
people have been able to see? You can never You can
never motivate God's people to do God's will by
fear. Say, in the days of thy power,
thy people shall be willing.
And then I read Benny Hinn. Benny Hinn said almost
the same thing. I think he just said that he has never done more than
3 hours. Did these people do it? Is it that God have different
standard for us in Africa? Because the story that me, I hear from— you
have to do 40 days. And I, I attended. I think that the max
marathon I've done is 21, above 21.
Praise God. I wanted to do 40, but I heard God. How many
of you have locked yourself up in the room and said that,
God, if you don't appear to me, I will die? I've said it
many times and I came out alive. Nobody will tell
you, you'll be the one that will know.
Amen. Glory to God. So what am I
saying? Whatever the
level you are presently, one thing you must
do away with to rise up on the wings of the Spirit is
condemnation,
and then find your reading.
Prayer. Because one thing that many people don't understand is this, you know,
God said that he gives the spirit of grace and
supplication. See, this thing, and he measures. Oh,
there are some people that the assignment, what God
wants to use them for— for example, you have table knife.
Then you have kitchen knife. Then there is the one that
butchers use. Then there are those that doctors use.
Different degree of sharpness. Now there
are some people, because of the kind of assignment that God have for Apostle
Ayodele Babalola, there is a certain dimension of
engine that God puts on the inside of him that you don't need.
Those are those here in the realm of the spirit, they are bulldozers.
You know what they call dozers? They are bulldozers. Their assignment
is to uproot iroko trees.
Now you, that your assignment is to wither the small, small grass, your own
role is not less important in the kingdom.
Apostle Ayobabala, this man— and really, that man
has a very strong prayer life. Imagine they hand over a microphone to you for
you to just close a prayer meeting, and then you close
it for 3 days. That's not normal.
Amen. Praise God.
But you, you can't cook such thing up.
You will have to be energized by a spirit.
The same thing is applicable to fasting. Every single time people did
40 days fasting in scripture, it was not out of sheer will. It is not
a formula. They were done with it and then they realized
that they have done 40 days because God
will have to release the spirit of grace and supplication.
Are you following what I'm saying? So he says all prayer. See, after me,
say all prayer louder. Say all prayer and
supplication in the Spirit, in the Spirit,
watching thereunto with all perseverance and supplication for
all saints. So the reason we encourage you to have certain
hours of prayer, on the minimum you pray daily,
is for you to maximize what you have in Christ Jesus.
It is for you to exercise yourself in the things of the Spirit,
because the matter will come up that will require you to tarry in the place
of prayer. If you have not exercised yourself consistently on daily
basis, you will not— if you faint in the days of
adversity, your strength is small.
So all of this is just to build a system that will enable
you to grow. Praise God forevermore.
Jude 20 says, but ye, beloved,
building up yourselves on your most holy
faith, praying in what? In the flesh?
In the Holy Ghost. So you see that every time
God talks about prayer in his word, it is with the
aid of Spirit. Now, when you are not conscious
of the ministry of the Holy Spirit, then you struggle.
Now, my point is that prayer, right from the Old Testament,
when God promised the Spirit, he let us understand that
he is going to come with the Spirit of grace and supplication.
You see it in 1 Corinthians chapter 14. Glory to God.
It says, how was it then? How we pray with the
Spirit and how we pray with understanding
also. When you are praying with the Spirit, what is going on? It is the
Holy Spirit supplying utterance,
supplying utterance. Praise God,
praise God. So all the scriptures shows
us one thing, that God never expects
you to have a prayer life. In fact,
he does not expect you to have a prayer moment
outside the help of the Holy Spirit.
So what I want to teach you this evening is how to respond
to the help of the Holy Spirit.
How to respond. You can learn all kinds of prayer,
you can listen to all teachings, but if
you do not know how to respond to the Spirit of grace and
supplication, you will still not have a
prayer life. Holy Spirit enables us
2 things God said in
that verse. He said he will give
you the spirit of one grace and
then supplication. This grace is an
enablement of the Holy Spirit.
Then supplication. Now what is supplication? Supplication is an
earnest petition made to
God.
Supplication, it's emphasizing
the earnest, the fervency with
which you make your petition known to God.
Glory to God.
Heartfelt, heartfelt request.
You see, you, you can pray, you can pray for, let's say,
maybe 10 minutes and generate more
results than you pray for 1 hour.
What makes the difference is how earnest the prayer is.
I think I once thought on this. When God sent Isaiah to tell Hezekiah
that he should pack up, he's going to die.
And Bible says that Hezekiah turned to the wall
and he didn't pray in tongues. He didn't
pray in tongues. He just, he just— that is petition.
Petition is a specific request.
It's a specific request. That specific
request that you have,
that, oh God, you know, one of the reasons
why I— and God forbid that you end this year without
the prophecy of the dream year not being fulfilled in your life, because see,
dream year is not a petition. There must be something
specific that reflects the
dream prophecy.
If the prayer is vague, it is not a petition.
Now, for those who have written petition to maybe
the police before, you know you have to be specific
on what you are writing petition on.
Oh, somebody is trying to claim your land, then you will have to,
in that petition, you have to state where the land is located,
when you bought the land. You will attach documents
that prove that you are the rightful owner of the property.
Then you have to talk about what they are doing to the land
and the specific thing you want the
government to intervene on.
Is that very clear? That is petition.
You know, interestingly, you know, Paul was writing to
the church and said, see, be anxious for nothing.
He said, but with what?
Prayer and supplication with
thanksgiving, make your petition
known unto God. So there
must be specificity. That is what makes it a petition.
Father, bless me. That's not petition.
Is that very clear? Oh, do you know that the gift of the Holy Ghost
is the blessing of Abraham? Oh, you didn't know that
we will receive the blessing of Abraham?
Which is the Holy Spirit.
Healing is a blessing. Are you still there? He said all spiritual blessings
in the heavenly places, but in petition
you've got to be specific. And you see,
the reason many people pray a prayer that is not heartfelt
is because there is no specification— no specificity,
rather. On that prayer. That's how
you press.
Brought the cause of the high. Our Father, as I go out today,
bless me, bless me, bless me, bless me, bless me,
bless me. How? He has
already blessed you, isn't it?
So a prayer for blessing It's not a petition.
He has already blessed you with all spiritual
blessings in the heavenly places. So when you
just say, Father, bless me, you are actually asking for what
he has already done. But now you want an outworking
of that blessing in your life.
Oh Father, bless my family with a new house.
We desire a 5-bedroom duplex.
That is petition.
Oh, thank you, Lord Jesus.
You've been writing application, you are not getting a
favorable response. And you
table the matter before the Lord, that is petition.
And one thing about petition is this, you stay on it
until you receive an answer of peace.
Are you following what I'm saying? So petition
is the specific request, the heartfelt prayer you
pray regarding those things. Is the supplication. Is that very clear?
So you cannot actually separate supplication from what?
From petition. So supplication is how
you pray. It is the intensity with
which you present your case before the Lord.
Glory to God. Thank you, Holy Spirit.
Thank you, Holy Spirit.
I want to just repeat this again. God never
intended, designed prayer
to be offered without the help of the Holy Spirit.
But are you yielding to this help?
Are you yielding to the Holy Spirit?
That's why I say you must never leave your day without conscious
awareness of the presence of the Holy Spirit.
There's something about awareness, it makes you to respond.
Now you can be in a house, you can be in a room with a
snake. As long as you don't know, you won't react to it.
I remember many years ago, I was— my mom told me to
go get something from a
particular spot in the room,
and as I lifted the basket, I saw a snake coiled
under the basket. I bolted.
So the man that came to kill the snake, he said, from the look of
things, this snake has actually been here for a very long time, but we never
knew. The same thing
is applicable to the things of the Spirit. When you are not conscious
of it, you cannot respond to it.
Some of you thought that you are prayerless, you don't have a
passion for prayer. It is not true.
You have— he says he has given you the Spirit whereby
you cry. So it means you can't cry without the Spirit.
Maybe I should run you through how the Holy Spirit aids you in prayer.
I taught on this last year during Rivers Camp Meeting. Glory to
God. The first thing the Holy Spirit helps you on
in prayer is to prompt you to pray.
Praise God!
The Holy Spirit prompts you to pray.
The Spirit of God creates or awakens
the desire to pray.
It sensitizes you.
It draws your attention to matters that require
urgent prayer. He prompts us
to pray. Now it doesn't matter how you feel
before the prompting comes. The one who prompts you to pray is
the one that will supply the grace and supplication.
But you see, most times we miss this ministry of the Holy Spirit because
we always look at ourselves. We always
look at ourselves. It doesn't matter how you felt,
it doesn't matter the feeling you have before
the prompting comes. All that God requires from you is to just yield.
He will take it up from there.
Just yield.
Sometimes you can just even say, Holy Spirit,
I know you want me to pray. I'm feeling so weak,
I'm feeling so fatigued, I don't feel like. Please help
me, help me,
and stay there. If you tell him to help
you, you don't walk away, just stay there.
A man of God asked Pastor Adeboye, he said, please, can you just give me
insight? Into your prayer life.
And Baba said that sometimes I am just in God's presence and
all I could just muster is Jesus,
Jesus, Jesus, Jesus,
Jesus, Jesus. Bible says the name of the Lord is a
strong tower. Oh, some of you don't even understand that if
Jesus is the only thing that you can say.
Oh, you don't understand that. See, sometimes God,
I beg can mean different things. Ah,
you don't know.
See, the one who have 20 prayer points
but just praying it— that's why sometimes you can almost
think that I am discouraging prayer points. Because, because many times when
you are prayer point oriented with your prayer
life, you will miss a lot.
In fact, the one that says, God, I beg endlessly.
Ha! I remember one time I learned this lesson from someone on a
mountain. You know, I, I, I think I told you tonight I used to go
on mountain to pray. And then I was praying not
too far from this guy, and this guy was just
the same prayer point. God,
have mercy. The way he was
saying is as if he's saying that, God, I beg God. And he
stayed with that prayer for days.
Are you getting what I'm saying here? It is harnessed. You see,
all the things you are calling, whatever you are saying, you are conveying
thoughts. Are you getting what
I'm saying here? You are simply conveying thoughts. So you, you don't have to
say the same thing a thousand ways. Bible says that
Jesus kept going back after coming to wake the disciples.
Bible says he went back to pray the same thing.
And I want to practice this. When you have a serious issue to
deal with, learn to pray a focused prayer that
even if you have other things— now that doesn't mean that you can actually bombard
God with so— like you can confuse heaven when your prayer point is too much.
It is not for sake of heaven, it is for the sake of your
own earnest prayer.
Like I said, Christians can be so deluded.
Christians are the only ones you will see who are
not praying, but they are surprised that their life is the way it is.
I don't even know what is going on. My job is not going the way
it is. My business— he, he's not praying. He blames everything
but himself.
And devil likes it. Praise God!
Oh, glory to God! Can you just pray in the spirit? Pray in the spirit.
Glory to God, glory to God,
glory to God. So before you start complaining,
ask yourself, have I truly prayed over this
We just catch ourselves that it's as if
we have been having too much conversation about this issue. But we have not prayed
about it, but it has never failed. I'm telling you, this is one of the
ways the devil has robbed many believers of the best that God
has for them. Devil will never mind, he will not
interfere in your conversation about the problem except
the attempt to pray about it.
Praise God. You know, I stumbled
on this scripture, you know, one time. Proverbs 19:3.
Proverbs 19:3.
It says, the foolishness
of a person ruins his way,
and his heart rages against the Lord.
The NIV says, a person's own folly leads to their
ruin, yet their heart rages against
God. One translation says that the foolishness of a man
destroys their life, then they turn to blame God. Praise God!
So the Holy Spirit prompts us, but you must learn how
to respond to this prompting.
He will pour out the Spirit of grace and supplication.
You must learn how to respond to it.
The reason it looks as if you don't have a prayer life, the reason
it looks as though you don't pray when you ought to, is because
you always rely on your own strength. You always judge
that moment by how you feel. There is supply.
And I'm telling you, the supply of God's Spirit is epichoregia.
Amen. Oh, glory to God. How many of you still
remember that teaching? My daughter was sharing that
message with me on— I mean, yesterday on the dining. I said, do you remember
the message you preached on epichoregia? I was like, how will you even be—
I had to rehearse the Greek word before I mastered it.
And you just say it casually like that.
The supply of the Spirit is not always at the level of
your need. It always surpasses
that. Even if you're at your lowest point, the supply of
the Spirit of grace will be so overwhelming that
you will float out of the valley.
But you must learn to respond to the prompting.
I've said it so many times that that sad
feeling— not every sad emotion is
a depression. Sometimes it is the
expression of the Holy Ghost through your emotion
that a battle is approaching. Rise up.
Because Holy Spirit does not just communicate to us through words alone.
Sometimes he communicates through emotion.
He has emotion. Bible says that do not grieve. You can
only grieve someone that has emotion.
So not every sad feeling is mood swing. Be spiritual.
That's how many people have fully sunk into
depression because they never understood
the emotion of the Spirit.
He's the one prompting you to pray.
Hallelujah! Are you getting what I'm saying here? He's the one prompting you
to pray. He awakens you.
He intimates you about what is— sometimes
you don't even know the reason why you're praying.
I remember one time I was, I was in my pastor's car,
we were driving from one town
to our base. We went for a meeting, it was
an all-night meeting, so after the meeting we were coming back to our
base. It was an interstate journey,
and I was, I was seated at the back with the kids.
The wife was seated beside him, and, you know,
of course he was driving. And we just got to a particular spot,
and I just have the prompting to pray.
You know, this is me in my pastor's car.
I do not want to sound so spiritual. I don't even know that kind of
setting. I don't want to appear as if I'm trying to
be spiritual. I'm in my pastor's car.
So I was suppressing it, but the urge was rising
strong. I just yielded to it and
I began to pray in tongues. It wasn't up to 10 minutes,
we ran into an accident. We hit a soldier.
Some of you have heard me tell the story a number of times. We hit
a soldier. In fact, we thought that the guy was dead.
You would never have met me if not for the help
of the Holy Spirit. That was the first and the only
time guns, rifles, about 6 or 7
of them were pointed at us.
And I was already saying my last prayer that God have mercy,
please let me make heaven, please let me make
heaven, please forgive all my sins.
And Holy Spirit told me, he said, if you had not yielded to
the prompting of the Holy Spirit, something else
would have happened. I told you, many times
bad things happen to good people because we allow the devil
to gain it starts,
before we are awakened to the consciousness that there
is warfare.
Just imagine, imagine you,
you, 2 people are, they are racing to a direction.
Let's say you are running from here to, uh, you're running
from here to Lekki Phase 1.
Now you thought that the person you are running with is around you,
but somehow you've been distracted and the person
is already somewhere around Chevron
or Orchid, and you are going to the same direction.
That person has head start.
Are you getting what I'm saying? So learn to respond to the promptings.
Many of you, when the Holy Spirit is prompting you, you look around you.
My children is fine, everything is fine. What is
going on? Some of you just feel like, why am I feeling like
this? What happened? What happened? Nothing happened now.
I didn't fight anybody. I don't have offense in my heart. Why am I feeling
this way? Can you just go and watch Sabinus Jare to lighten the mood?
Now you watch Sabinus, you watch everything, that thing
is still hanging. You can only dissipate
such burden in the place of prayer. And I'm
telling you that never judge by
how you feel. Even when you don't feel like praying, just yield
to his help. Because God never planned that
you have a prayer life outside the Holy Spirit.
Not even a prayer life. He never intended that you will have any
prayer moment. He said all prayer, always. In the spirit.
So the Holy Spirit is always there. Even when I
sense the burden in the bedroom, even when I am in
the toilet— there's nowhere you find yourself,
just trust the Holy Spirit. Because what gives potency to your
prayer is not the words you speak, it is the utterance that
the Holy Spirit is supplying.
Some of the people that have the funniest sound of tongue are
the most dangerous people.
Oh, glory to God. So you don't
judge potency by the vocabularies.
And I'm telling you, see,
we don't always speak the same tongue.
Now I'm even talking about myself. Sometimes the
tongue you hear me speak in church is different from the one that comes out
of my mouth in the place of prayer.
You know, I was praying one day and
the person I was praying with had to record. Now, this is many
years ago. I was still an undergraduate. I think I was in 300 level,
and the person had to record the prayer.
He said, very— I don't understand.
Listen to— like, he said
the person kept that prayer on their phone for a very
long time. In fact, they use it for ringing tone. Even me myself, I heard.
I was like, did this thing come out of my mouth?
It is you praying with all the earnestness
you can gather in your heart.
Glory to God. The Holy Spirit also
supplies utterance. Now I'm telling you the
ministry, what the Spirit of God supplies.
What this spirit of grace and supplication
does to you regarding prayer. So what's the first thing?
It prompts you. Then the second thing is that it supplies
utterance. Acts chapter 2, Bible says that the
Holy Ghost gave them utterance,
but they did the speaking. They spoke as the Holy
Spirit gave them utterance. So what the Holy Spirit gives you is
utterance. This utterance is breath of the Spirit.
That is where the power lies.
The power is not in the vocabulary, it is in the
breath that comes out of your spirit. That breath is the cry.
Utterance And in this utterance,
it is only to your understanding that this utterance is
not intelligible. This utterance is intelligible
to the ears of God. Bible says that the one who
knows the hearts of men— oh,
praise God forevermore! Let's go back to Romans chapter
8. Thank you, Lord Jesus.
And he that searcheth the hearts knows
what is in the mind of the Spirit, because he
maketh intercession for the saints according to the will of God.
According to the will of God. Now let me show you something in the book
of 1 Corinthians.
Thank you, Father. Oh, glory to God.
Glory, glory, glory to God. Verse 10: For
to us God revealed them through his Spirit, for the
Spirit searches all things, even the
depths of God. Glory to God.
The Spirit does what? He searches all things,
even the depths of God. The Holy Ghost knows
the depths of God's plan for your life.
Now you are there, you are dreaming to have a dream
year, a dream year with a great job,
a dream year with your own apartment where
you are no longer answerable to any lawyer, a dream
year where you now have your SUV.
And that is your dream. Yeah, but Bible says the Holy Spirit knows
the depths of God,
because what is in your mind are the surface
things, the surface plan of God for your life,
the one that your mind can easily interpret. But I'm
telling you, there are depths to God's plan for your life, and Holy Spirit knows
about all things. He knows
about all things. Hallelujah!
Praise God! Say, the Holy Spirit— hey,
come on, louder! Say, the Holy Spirit searches
all things, even the deep things
of God. Oh my God, the deep things of
God, the deep plans of God for my
life. Those are the utterances supplied unto you in the place of prayer.
If you leave your prayer life to your understanding, you'll only be asking for the
things that your mind can relate with, and you can only ask
for what you know.
Glory to God. Now just imagine, just, just imagine
that you, you tell a woman,
an old woman that is illiterate, that lives in
a village, that has never in her life,
never in her life heard of iPhone before, and you say
that, uh, Mama, which one will you want,
iPhone 17 or Nokia? Do you know that if she's
familiar with Nokia, she will definitely go for Nokia because that is
what he knows? There are best things in God's for your life
you don't know. So if you leave your prayer life to
what your understanding can process, you will miss the
best things that is in the plan of God for your life.
And so when the Holy Spirit supplies utterance, this utterance
is communicating the deep things unto God.
Praise God forevermore. It is
an encrypted conversation. Now Paul
says in Romans that God knows the hearts.
He knows the hearts of men. He knows
what is in the mind of the Spirit. The Spirit too knows what is
in the mind of God. Oh, you didn't get that?
Bible says in Romans 8 that the Spirit—
I'm sorry, Romans 8:26-27 rather— that
God knows the mind of the Spirit. He knows the thoughts
of the Spirit. In that utterance you are speaking,
God can pick the information. He knows it. Now, where does
the information come from? The information comes from the research of the Holy
Spirit about God's plan for your life.
Let me give you an example here. It is just like Isaac
is asking for venison. His wife is the
one that is helping you to prepare the venison.
Rebecca knows because Rebecca was
the one that created the recipe that Isaac fell in love
with. She's been cooking for Isaac long
before they were conceived. There's no way Jacob could
have beat the recipe of his mother.
Rebekah knows the mind of Isaac.
So Isaac says, I want venison.
The one who knows the mind of Isaac prepares it and handed
it over to Jacob to present it to the father.
That is what the Holy Spirit does. He knows the
mind of the Father. He will give you the expo that
these are the things that God has in plan for your life. You are asking
for cars, but God want to give you a factory. So don't ask for those
things. Come and take this. Get this.
Present it to the Father. He can't say no to
it.
Praise God forevermore. Glory to God.
Oh, what a sweet Holy Spirit. Why won't
you, why won't you respond to this spirit of grace and supplication?
For who among you knows, for who among people
knows the thoughts of a person except the spirit of the person that
is in him? Who also knows the thoughts of God?
Who? So also the thoughts of God no one knows
except the Spirit of God.
Nobody knows except the Spirit of God. So when the
Holy Spirit gives you utterance, it is in precision concerning
God's plan for your life. You can't pray amiss when you pray in the spirit.
It gives you the utterance. The same thing you are
speaking, the same vocabulary you are speaking when you are asking for a particular petition,
it sounded the same way you're asking for another thing, but you are communicating
totally 2 different things. Are you getting
what I'm saying here? Then the Spirit of God gives you
burden. He gives us burden,
especially for intercession. He distributes
burden. I love something that Paul says. He said that I may know him,
the power of his resurrection,
the fellowship of his suffering. So there
are times that the Holy Spirit will share burdens with you,
and that's what I was talking about. That is, not every sad feeling
really means that something bad is going on in your life. Sometimes it
could be that God is sensitizing you on something that is about to happen,
or God wants you to intercede for somebody.
Praise God! Oh, glory to God!
Glory to God, glory to God,
glory to God. And the last thing,
it quickens us. Let's see Psalm 80.
This is one of my favorite scriptures. Psalm 80:18.
Verse 18, it says— I
love the KJV translation of that verse.
It says, so will not we go back from thee.
Quicken us, and we will call upon
thy name. Quicken us and
we will call upon thy name. Quicken us,
invigorate us, revive us.
So you can't call upon God except he quickens you.
See, if you can go listen to this message again and again
and you— your prayer life does not
pick up, I don't know what else can help you. It is the Holy Spirit
that will help you. He said, quicken us that we may call
upon you. And the way God quickens us is by the spirit
of grace and supplication, which means that he vitalizes
us, he energizes us in the place of prayer.
You will be so shocked that you have missed so many prayer opportunities because
you thought you were weak. If only you could just yield to the Holy
Spirit, even even in that state of weakness, and then you realize the amount
of energy that you could dispense in the
place of prayer. It is the Holy Spirit, it is not you.
So you just learn how to respond to the Spirit of God.
Tell your neighbor, say, learn to respond. Learn to respond.
Be vulnerable to the Holy Spirit. Stop packaging to the Spirit of
God. Be vulnerable to God's Spirit,
then stay there. Is that very clear? Stay there.
Never be in haste. Sometimes Kenneth
Hagin said that sometimes it could be after 30
minutes, sometimes it could be as long as 1 hour before
he feels that quickening. But stay there.
Is that very clear? This is the most practical thing you will hear
from me today. If you want to respond to the ministry,
to the supply of the Holy Spirit, don't ask for his help and walk
away. Ask for his help and stay there.
Just stay there. Even when that tongues
sound mechanical, just stay there.
Is that very clear? Stay there.
Even when you don't feel like, even when you feel it is forced,
just stay there and keep your mouth moving.
Keep your mouth moving. Keep your mouth moving. Oh,
before you know what is happening, you have stood up. Before you know what is
happening, you're already pacing the floor. Before you know what is happening,
you're already scattering everywhere. But you will never get to that point
if you don't stay there. Tell anybody, say, stay there.
Say, stay there until the help comes.
The Holy Spirit helps us to pray, and he's helping
you today. Rise on your feet. He's helping.